Finding Aid for Chia-Shun Yih papers, 1930-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Chia-Shun Yih papers 1930-1997
Yih, Chia-Shun, 1918-1997.
1 oversize folders
4 linear feet
97121 Aa 2; UAm
Papers of Chia-Shun Yih, internationally respected scientist and Stephen P. Timoshenko Distinguished Professor Emeritus of Fluid Mechanics at the University of Michigan. Series in the collection are Biographical, Correspondence, Research and Writings, and Visual Materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Shirley A. Yih and Katherine Yih (Donor no. 8632 ). Original donation was made in 1997 with additional donations coming throughout 2007 and early 2008.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Chia-Shun Yih, internationally respected scientist and Stephen P. Timoshenko Distinguished Professor Emeritus of Fluid Mechanics at the University of Michigan, was born in 1918 in Kweiyang, Kweichow Province, China. After graduating in 1942 from the National Central University in Nanking, Yih worked as a research assistant at the National Hydraulic Laboratory in Quanshien, as an engineer at the National Bureau of Bridge Design, and as an instructor at the National University of Kweichow. Selected by the Ministry of Education to study in the United States, he entered the University of Iowa in 1946, earning his M.S. in 1947 and Ph.D. in 1948. He taught at various universities in North America and France before joining the faculty of the University of Michigan as an associate professor in 1956. Two years later, he was promoted to professor of fluid mechanics. In 1967, he was chosen to give the Henry Russel Lecture--the highest honor the university bestows upon a senior faculty member.
Yih's published work covers a broad range of material, including well over 100 scientific papers and several books including Dynamics of Nonhomogeneous Fluids (1960), later revised as Stratified Flows (1980), and Fluid Mechanics, A Concise Introduction to the Theory (1969) as well as an anthology of Selected Papers. His numerous honors include the National Science Foundation Senior Postdoctoral Fellowship (1958), the Guggenheim Fellowship (1964), the 1968 Achievement Award from the Chinese Institute of Engineers of New York, the 1973 Achievement Award from the Chinese Engineers and Scientists Association of Southern California, the Alexander von Humboldt Senior Scientist Award (Germany, 1977-78), the Theodore von Karman Medal (American Society of Civil Engineers, 1981), the Stephan S. Attwood Award (University of Michigan, 1984), the Fluid Dynamics Prize (American Physical Society, 1985), and the Otto Laporte Award (American Physical Society, 1985). He was elected Fellow of the American Physical Society, a member of the National Academy of Engineering, and a member of the Academia Sinica (the Chinese National Academy of Science in Taiwan). A much sought after speaker at major universities and symposia around the world, Yih lectured in French and German, as well as Chinese and English.
In a 1977 letter to a friend, Chia Shun-Yih wrote, "For me, the criterion of science is truth, but its motivation resides in a sense of beauty -- and in that it is like art." Yih's interests extended to a lively interest in nature and the arts, including Chinese and Western literature and painting. He died in April of 1997. In July of that year colleagues and friends attended a memorial celebration symposium sponsored by the College of Engineering and the Chia-Shun Yih Lectureship Fund. A videotape of the symposium proceedings is part of the collection.
The Chia-Shun Yih collection represents the life and work of an internationally known scientist who spent a significant portion of his career at the University of Michigan. The papers offer the most richness to those researchers interested in mechanics and hydraulics, a field in which Yih made major contributions, but they also include contain glimpses into the broad range of interests he cultivated throughout the years in literature and the arts.
Subjects:
Yih, Chia-Shun, 1918-1997.; Fluid dynamics.; Fluid mechanics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Engineering Mechanics.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Yih, Chia-Shun, 1918-1997.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.; Photographs.
- Biographical
  Within the Biographical folders there are letters of recommendations for numerous awards and award notifications; awards, CVs and publication lists, lists of Yih's students, colleagues and friends; and letters of condolence sent to the family at the time of Yih's death -- many thoughtfully reflective of his life and work.
  - General 1958-1980 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Honors
    - Academia Sinica certificate 1990 (Folder 1)
    - General, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - C.S. Yih Memorial Symposium (13th U.S. National Congress of Applied Mechanics) 1998 (Box 1)
    - Fluid Dynamics Lectureship 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - G.I. Taylor Lecture 1992 (Box 1)
    - Henry Russell Lectureship 1974 (Box 1)
    - Symposium on Fluid Mechanics Honoring C-S Yih 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Tribute to Yih by Professor Tsutahara 1997 (Box 1)
    - Yih Memorial Lectureship 1997 (Box 1)
  - Biography of C.S. Yih by Y.C. Fung (Box 1)
  - Curricula Vitae and Publication Lists (Box 1)
  - Graduate Students (Box 1)
  - Journals 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Service/Symposium and Condolences (Box 1)
  - Transcripts, Naturalization Papers, etc. 1930s-1950s (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1956-1996
  Correspondence forms the heart of the collection, mainly covering the years 1958 to 1997. Correspondents from around the world and across the nation include prominent Chinese-American scientists (such as physicist Ta-You Wu, a University of Michigan graduate who trained two Nobel laureates) and numerous colleagues eminent in the field of fluid mechanics. A folder entitled "From University File" chronicles Yih's career at Michigan --- from a letter negotiating his move to Ann Arbor in 1956 to his retirement in 1988 when the Regents named him the Stephen P. Timoshenko Distinguished University Professor Emeritus of Fluid Mechanics.
  - General 1957-1997, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - In Chinese, Miscellaneous Undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Charles Vest 1990-1997 (Box 2)
  - From University File 1956-1988 (Box 2)
  - G.I. (Geoffrey Ingram) Taylor 1956-1977 (Box 2)
  - Otto Laporte Memorial Lectures 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Peer Review Correspondence 1984-1996 (Box 2)
- Research and Writings
  Research and Writings series consists of some of Yih's writings and lectures and is divided into two subseries, Manuscript and Published. The Manuscript subseries includes manuscripts and typescripts of articles and lectures, mostly from within the last decade or so of his career, including the last piece Yih published during his lifetime, "Evolution of Darwinian Drift," and work prepared for the 1996 conference on hydrodynamics in Hong Kong. There is also a copy of "Old China Remembered," which appeared in Ohio Review in 1977. Donald Hall, in an introduction to the article, wrote poetically of his friendship with Chia-Shun Yih, formed in the sixties when both were teaching in Ann Arbor. The Published subseries includes copies of a number of Yih's published books and textbooks.
  - Manuscript
    - "Added Mass" 1995 (Box 2)
    - Beijing Lectures (in Chinese) 1983 (Box 2)
    - Collected Articles (not by Yih) 1968-1982 (Box 2)
    - C.S. Yih Reader, 2006 (Box 2)
    - "Evolution of Darwinian Drift" 1997 (Box 2)
    - Foreword to a Book (in Chinese) (Box 2)
    - "General Solution for Interaction of Solitary Waves Including Head-On Collisions" (Box 2)
    - "A General Solution for Three-Dimensional Nonlinear Waves" (Box 2)
    - "Intermodal Interaction of Internal Solitary Waves" 1992 (Box 2)
    - "Iowa: A Remembrance and a Perspective" Lecture (Box 2)
    - "Kinetic-energy Mass, Momentum Mass, and Drift Mass in Steady Irrotational Subsonic Flows" 1995 (Box 2)
    - Lecture Transparencies (Box 2)
    - "Linear and Nonlinear Waves in Flowing Water" (Box 2)
    - Literary Writing (Box 2)
    - Notes 1996, 1987, Undated, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - PhD Dissertation--"Free Convection Due to a Point Source of Heat" 1948 (Box 3)
    - "Plane Couette Flow is Stable" (Box 3)
    - "The Role of Drift Mass in the Kinetic Energy and Momentum of Periodic Water Waves and Sound Waves" 1996 (Box 3)
    - Selected Papers by Chia-Shun Yih Fliers (Box 3)
    - Second International Conference on Hydrodynamics December 16-19, 1996 (Box 3)
    - "Solitary Waves in Poiseville Flow of Rotating Fluids" 1992 (Box 3)
    - "Standing Cnoidal Waves" (Box 3)
    - "Tornado-Like Flows" (Box 3)
    - "Weak Interaction of Multi-directional Nonlinear Water Waves" 1996 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (includes "Old China Remembered") (Box 3)
  - Published
    - 13th U.S. National Congress of Applied Mechanics (Box 3)
    - Dynamics of Nonhomogeneous Fluids (Box 3)
    - Fluid Dynamics at Interfaces (Box 3)
    - Fluid Mechanics (3 editions) (Box 4)
    - Research Publications of Chia-Shun Yih Recipient of the 1985 APS Prize in Fluid Dynamics (Box 4)
    - Selected Papers by Chia-Shun Yih, 2 volumes (Box 4)
- Audio-Visual Materials
  Visual Materials consist of audiotapes and a CD, photographs, and videotapes. The several photographs are portraits of Yih, group images, and a few snapshots. Researchers interested in both the work and the life of Yih will find the videotapes of the Symposium and Memorial Celebration held in his honor on July 31, 1997 at the University of Michigan of particular interest. The program consisted of readings of professional papers; reminiscences by a long time friend, Yuan-Cheng Fung; and personal remembrances from among the many friends and colleagues who held Chia-Shun Yih in high esteem.
  - Audio (1985 Symposium and 1986 Birthday Dinner) (Box 4)
  - Photographs (Box 4)
  - Yih Symposium, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 4)